Guide to the John Johnston Papers, 1833 - 1877, 1919-1920
John Johnston Papers, 1833 - 1877, 1919-1920
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Johnston, John, 1806-1879.
1000-144
0.75
2
John Johnston was a professor of natural sciences at Wesleyan University, and twice served as its acting president.
The John Johnston Papers include correspondence, biographical information, materials about the study of science at Wesleyan University, and a scrapbook of programs from 19th century Wesleyan events.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions. However, the scrapbook is extremely fragile and should be handled with care.
Acquisitions Information
Two autograph notes in folder 8 were the gift of Robert Maas, 1980
Items in folders 1-6, 9-10, and 13-15 were the gift of Robert J. Williams, great-grandson of John Johnston, 1987-1988.
Other materials assembled by John Spaeth, University Archivist.
Alternate Finding Aids
An older, printed finding aid with a complete list of correspondents is available for use in Special Collections & Archives.
Biographical Note
John Johnston was born in Bristol, Maine and received his B.A. and M. A. degrees from Bowdoin College. Before coming to Wesleyan, he taught at Cazenovia Seminary (Oneida Conference) in New York from 1832-1835. At Wesleyan, Johnston began as Assistant Professor of Mathematics and Lecturer in Natural Science in 1837, was Professor of Natural Science from 1837-1873, and Professor Emeritus from 1873 until his death in 1879. Johnston was acting President of Wesleyan twice in this period. Her served in 1851-1852, prior to the presidency of Augustus William Smith, and in 1857-1858 following Smith's presidency.
Collection Overview
The John Johnston Papers include correspondence, biographical information, materials about the study of science at Wesleyan University, and a scrapbook of programs from 19th century Wesleyan events.
The correspondence of John Johnston contains much interesting material on and around the formative years of Wesleyan University. Many of the letters deal with science (fossils and minerals); the teaching of science (textbooks, lab experiments, and equipment); letters of inquiry and requests for catalogs from prospective students; addresses at commencement; and contributions to Frankfort Mineral Cabinet. The collection is especially useful on the topics of science and science vis a vis Methodism at the dawning of Darwinism. Other letters in the collection discuss the Civil War and Wesleyan University.
The correspondence of J.G. Blair is notably interesting for comments on the Civil War and on science education in relation to religion, or inquiries into the mysteries of God's great laboratory. (January 27, 1863)
A. Rollins' letter for February 3 is an interesting diatribe on the suspect morals of a Wesleyan student. A letter (May 6, 1851) from M. C. White from China contains the flavor of his life as a missionary as he tries to preach in Chinese on Sundays, Tuesdays, and Thursdays in a little room opening to the street between the river and the south gate of the city. Many of the J. Holdich letters of the 1860s deal with the politics as well as the sorrow of the war. Among other Johnston correspondents are Nathan Bangs, Cyrus Foss, Joseph Cummings, the Hoyts, and Orange Judd.
Collection Arrangement
Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Johnston, John, 1806-1879.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Administration.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Faculty.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History--19th century.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Presidents.; Natural history--United States--History--19th century.
Related Material
Register of Meteorological Observations Made in Middletown, by Augustus Smith, John Johnston, and H. D. A. Ward, 1849-1890 (lacks September 1852-January 1858). Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan Museum Records. Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Vertical (reference) File on John Johnston. Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Several letters from John Johnston can be found in the William North Rice Papers. Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
A letter to John Johnston can be found in the Willbur Fisk Papers. Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University.
Letters and documents referring to John Johnston's book, A History of the Towns of Bristol and Bremen in the State of Maine, including the Pemaquid Settlement, were sent by Robert Williams to the Harrington Meeting House, Pemaquid, Maine.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Correspondence
  - 1842-1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    96 letters to John Johnston.
  - 1862-1869 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    79 letters to John Johnston.
  - Orange Judd to John Johnston, June 24, 1851 and October 18, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Undated correspondence (Box 1, Folder 4)
    17 letters to John Johnston. Filed alphabetically.
  - Civil War letter from John Johnston to C. D. Hubbard, May 30, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exchange of letters between a Johnston grandson and a Hubbard son regarding Civil War letter, December 1919-January 1920.
  - John Johnston to J. M. Reid about publishing an article, May 14, 1853-July 18, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    11 letters.
  - John Johnston to J. M. Reid about proposed nominees for professorships, 1859-1860
    4 letters.
  - John Johnston letter of recommendation for student, May 14, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John Johnston to Stephen Olin, May 1, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Written from the American Association of Geologists and Naturalists Meeting at Albany, NY.
  - John Johnston to Good _____, November 28, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Regarding settling of note.
  - John Johnston to Stephen Olin, July 17, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Regarding Middletown and Vicinity Bible Society.
  - John Johnston to Good _____, October 20, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Regarding printing delays on Johnston's work on Natural Philosophy, October 20, 1845.
  - Note to John Johnston as registrar, August 5, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Student honorably dismissed, August 8, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - D. W. Clark to John Johnston, June 3, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Regarding the Legacy of Bishop Hedding.
  - John Johnston to Mrs. Olin, February 20, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Regarding Henry Olin's mumps.
  - John Johnston to Mrs. Olin, June 28, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Thanking Mrs. Olin for contribution to mineral case.
  - Invitation to John Johnston from Charles R. North, February 16, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Invitation to first annual dinner of the New York Wesleyan University Club.
  - John Johnston autograph notes, October 26, 1847 and November 1, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Envelopes addressed to Third Assistant Post Master General, Washington.
  - List of Wesleyan names (Box 1, Folder 9)
    2 pages. Signature unreadable.
  - Letters of introduction from W. S. Smyth to Dr. Cummings, June 30, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letters of introduction for prospective students.
- Series 2: Biographical/Personal/Wesleyan Administrative
  - Miscellaneous works about John Johnston (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Portraits (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Minor publications (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Documents related to John Johnston, 1824-1876 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Character references, letters certifying teacher qualifications, records of donations, honors, awards, memberships, and official commission as State Chemist (January 10, 1872).
  - Annual report as acting president, 1851-1852 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Penciled Trustee minutes on funeral arrangements of Stephen Olin, August 18, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Abstract of Annual Financial Report, April 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Written by John Johnston, Registrar. Includes description of Wesleyan's real and moveable property.
  - John Johnston letter to Treasurer, August 17, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - John Johnston letters to Financial Committee, April 1856, July 1856 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    2 letters, which request money.
- Series 3: Wesleyan Scientific
  - Report on natural history collections, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Inventory of apparatus, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Committee on Apparatus reports, 1860, 1862-1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bills, expenditures, 1836-1844, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Appropriation request, 1839 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Frankfort Cabinet of Minerals, 1857-1863 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Payments, subscriptions.
  - Frankfort Cabinet of Minerals, 1860-1863 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Reports
  - John Johnston letter to the Joint Board, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Discusses adding personal mineral collection to the Wesleyan Mineral Cabinet.
  - Pressed botanical specimens (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Removed from two volumes of the Maine Wesleyan Journal from Johnston's own library.
  - Loose scrapbook items, 1872-1874 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    These items were loose in the scrapbook found in Box 2.
- Series 4: Scrapbook
  The items in the scrapbook are pasted in chronologically, but they have been listed here by type. Items dating from 1872 to 1874 were loose, and can be found in Box 1, Folder 24.
  - Commencement programs, 1833, 1836-1874 (Box 2)
  - Senior Exhibition programs, 1834-1842 (Box 2)
    See also Anniversary Exercise programs.
  - Anniversary (Annual) Exercise programs, 1843-1872, 1874 (Box 2)
    The Anniversary Exercises took the place of Senior Exhibitions in 1843.
  - Junior Exhibition programs, 1834, 1836, 1838, 1840-1841, 1843-1867, 1869-1872 (Box 2)
  - Sophomore Exhibition programs, 1858-1868, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Declamation of Junior and Sophomore Classes programs, 1847-1852, 1854-1855, 1857 (Box 2)
  - Prize Declamation programs, 1858-1863, 1865-1866, 1868-1871, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Prize Contest in Debate and Declamation, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Class Day programs, 1865, 1868-1869, 1871 (Box 2)
  - Order of Exams programs, 1859-1863, 1865-1866
  - Rich Prize programs, 1868-1870 (Box 2)
  - Rich Hall Dedication program, 1868 (Box 2)
  - Laying of Cornerstone for Judd Hall program, 1870 (Box 2)
  - Phi Nu Theta 8th Quadrennial Anniversary, 1870 (Box 2)